Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף נ"א, daf
nun alef, 51, and we're in the middle of the discussion of
the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about what is the
order of the four executions of בית דין, Beis Din, but since
a core basis or nexus of that debate is how to explain
under what circumstances the כהן, kohen, the daughter of the כהן kohen
who fornicates, who commits adultery, whatever, that she gets the punishment of
שריפה, sreifa, and which situations does she get שריפה sreifa sort of
tells us how these various executions rank, and therefore it becomes a
nexus of the debate of the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. Today's דף daf is going to focus really totally on this
issue about the burning of the daughter of the כהן, kohen, and
to sort of not just for the sake of understanding the order
of the מיתות בית דין, misas beis din, of the executions of
the court, but just for its own sake as well. Okay, so
why don't we pick up with the top of נ"א עמוד א'?
nun alef amud alef? It's middle of a ברייתא braisa which we
were in the middle of yesterday, so we won't read the beginning
of it, but we'll start from the very top of נ"א עמוד
א'. nun alef amud alef. אין לי אלא שנישואה לכהן. Ein li
ela shenisuah l'kohen. So I know that the גמרא Gemara yesterday said
I know it's talking about an act of forbidden sexual acts because
it says לזנות, liznot, so it's not just something like לחלל חילול
שבת. lechalel chillul shabbat. I know that she's married because of a
link of the word אביה aviha here and the נערה המאורסה. na'arah
hameurasah. Fine. So that's why I know that we're talking about a
married woman who commits adultery. אין לי אלא שנישואה לכהן. Ein li
ela shenisuah l'kohen. Now I only know if she's married and she's
committing adultery to whom is she married. Maybe she would only be
the case where she's married to a כהן kohen and then she
maybe has her full כהונה kehunah status still associated with her. So
there's more of a את אביה היא מחללת, as aviha hi mechallelet,
more of a desecration of not only committing of adultery but a
desecration of her כהונה kehunah status when she does so. נישואה ללוי
לישראל עובד כוכבים חלל ממזר נתין מנילן? Nisuah l'Levi, l'Yisrael, oveid kochavim,
chalal, mamzer, nesin minalan? How do I know even if she's married
to one of these people, a לוי, Levi, a ישראל Yisrael who's
just not a כהן, kohen, and then the non-Jew, the חלל, chalal,
ממזר, mamzer, and the נתין nesin are people that it's forbidden for
her to be married to? Okay, by the עובד כוכבים oveid kochavim
it's particularly shocking because it sounds like, and this גמרא Gemara doesn't
explore it, it's explored elsewhere, it sounds like it would be a
binding marriage that if she was married to an עובד כוכבים oveid
kochavim to a non-Jew then it would be an act of adultery
to be sleeping with somebody else. Right? We always assumed that married
to a non-Jew, certainly that's the הלכה, halakhah, it's not a binding
marriage. So whatever sin she did in doing that act of married
to a non-Jew, it would not be an act of adultery to
be sleeping with another man. So but our גמרא Gemara does not
unpack that. The חלל chalal is somebody it's not permitted for her
to be married to but it's a כהן kohen who has lost
sort of the קדושה kedushah of כהונה. kehunah. And therefore for example
the child of a כהן kohen and a גרושה, gerushah, that would
be one example. So that would not be forbidden for her to
be married to, but it would make her a חללה chalalah in
the process. And a ממזר mamzer and נתין, nesin, נתין nesin we'll
sort of bracket, were they Jewish, had they converted, had they not
converted, but ממזר mamzer certainly is somebody that it is forbidden for
her to be married to and the marriage is binding. So you
actually have a wide range here, right? The עובד כוכבים, oveid kochavim,
it's not binding, but we're sort of ignoring that right now. The
חלל, chalal, it's a legitimate marriage but it makes her a חללה.
chalalah. And the ממזר, mamzer, it's not a legitimate marriage but the
marriage is binding. Okay, now how do I know in all of
these cases where there's something problematic about the marriage to begin with?
How do I know that even in that case she's liable and
the same punishment would apply? תלמוד לומר ובת איש כהן. Talmud lomar
u'vat ish kohen. So the extra maybe ו, vav, ובת, u'vat, or
maybe it's the fact that it says איש כהן ish kohen and
it doesn't say that she's a כהנת. kohenet. So אף על פי
שאינה כהנת, af al pi she'eina kohenet, even if something has done
to compromise her own כהונה kehunah status. We said the very phrase
כהנת kohenet is funny, normally a woman is not considered a כהנת,
kohenet, she's a בת כהן, bat kohen, she's an אשת כהן, eshet
kohen, but here it's saying that nevertheless that's the point, ובת איש
כהן, u'vat ish kohen, she was a daughter of a כהן kohen
even if somehow her own כהונה kehunah status has been somehow compromised.
Okay, that still even so, it's still an act of adultery, she's
still the daughter of a כהן, kohen, there's still a desecration of
her status even though it's already been somewhat compromised, and therefore she
gets this punishment. Okay, now we continue. Okay, so it says ובת
איש כהן כי תחל לזנות את אביה היא מחללת, u'vat ish kohen
ki teichel liznot et aviha hi mechallelet, she is desecrating her father,
באש תשרף. ba'esh tisareif. So here's a דרשה drasha which we referred
to yesterday. היא בשריפה, Hi bisreifa, the extra word היא hi means
she'll get burnt, ואין בועליה בשריפה, v'ein bo'aleha bisreifa, but the man
who committed adultery with her, he is a man who committed adultery
and the normal punishment for adultery would be חנק, chenek, would be
strangulation, or if it's a נערה המאורסה na'arah hameurasah it would be
סקילה. skilah. But anyway, it would not be שריפה. sreifa. שריפה sreifa
is unique not to the sin of adultery but to her, what
she has done in the process. She brought shame or she desecrated
her father's house. So although the man was sort of who she
slept with... was the means for her to do that, but this
is unique, that's the emphasis of היא. hi. Only she gets this
specific punishment of שרפה. sreifah. For everybody else, it's like a normal
act of adultery. היא בשרפה ואין בועלה בשרפה. Hi bi'sreifah ve'ein boalah
bi'sreifah. היא בשרפה Hi bi'sreifah similarly ואין זוממיה בשרפה. ve'ein zomemeha bi'sreifah.
If they are עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, they don't get שרפה. sreifah.
Now again, that's bizarre, because עדים זוממים edim zomemim never did the
act, but they're punished as if they did the act. But presumably
it seems to be that this is somehow related to their gender,
right? Because if an עד זומם, ed zomem, like you could imagine,
if an עד זומם ed zomem testified that a guy committed murder,
it's like they committed murder. If he testified that a guy committed
adultery or a woman committed adultery, it's like they committed adultery. But
you cannot say that it's like they did this, brought this shame
on their father's house, because that's something unique to something a woman
could do, okay, in this context, not something a man could do.
So you could make them into adulterers and punish them with the
punishment that the act of adultery would have, but not the unique
act of, like, bringing the shame onto the father's house. Yes.
So all women adulteresses get burning?
No, all בת איש כהן bat ish kohen adulteresses
get burning.
Right.
Please! So it's maybe not gender, it may be her role or
her status or whatever. Right, but it was the gender. All women
adulterers...
no, gender is necessary but not sufficient. Meaning there is no, right,
there, a woman could commit adultery without this status of בת איש
כהן, bat ish kohen, etc., without שרפה, sreifah, right? But then, but
so you have to be uniquely in this role of being the
בת איש כהן, bat ish kohen, right? But within that, so it's
just like, so okay, why don't we assign that to the זוממים,
zomemim, you know?
So why do we assign it to the בן איש כהן? ben
ish kohen?
Why, what, we don't. Right, right.
But not all women get the same punishment, right? So there's something
unique about maybe the כהונה. kehunah.
I agree, I agree.
It's a multiplicity of factors. Right. Anyway, I'm just trying to figure
out why is it, you know, if somebody says, I don't know,
if עדים זוממים edim zomemim testified that a כהן, kohen, you know,
I don't know, ate תרומה trumah or something like that, right, or
if he ate תרומה טמאה, trumah tmei'ah, a כהן, kohen, I don't
know, did the עבודה avodah when he was a טמא tamei or
something of that nature. Something that they couldn't do because they're not
כהנים, kohanim, right, but would you still apply the same punishment to
the עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, even if they never have that identity
that of the person they're testifying about that. So it's very bizarre
that this is the one case in all things עדים זוממים edim
zomemim could testify about, and, you know, even many, many things that's
not relevant to them you'd apply the punishment, but here you don't.
So, right, it's not so deliberate. Yes. But if there is a
situation of a woman adulterer not a בת כהן, bat kohen, yes,
and there's עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, do they get her punishment?
Yes, but that's her punishment would be the same as the man's
punishment. Okay, so they do get her punishment.
But it's the gender... thank you. The gender is not the thing
separated out, it's the כהונה kehunah family that makes it complicated.
All right. We we can talk about this more later. It's both.
If you just had, right, it's both. It's the combination. Right.
Parallel sin, then they get something else.
Right. All right, we'll move on. Okay. Anyway, it's it's unusual that
this is the one thing that the עדים זוממים edim zomemim do
not get the punishment even though in other areas, it could also
be things that isn't relevant to them, you'd apply the
punishment, but here you don't. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, את אביה בשרפה ואת חמיה בסקילה. et
aviha bi'sreifah ve'et chamiha bi'skilah. Her father, with her father it's שרפה,
sreifah, with her father-in-law it's סקילה. skilah. That's a very curious statement
and we'll try to figure out what that means in a bit.
So that's the end of the ברייתא. braita. Now let's unpack this
תוספתא. Tosefta. אמר מר, Amar Mar, יכול אפילו חילול שבת, Yachol afilu
chillul Shabbos, so we're now going to go back and unpack the
תוספתא Tosefta that we just quoted. Here by the way, I make
this comment but it's been a while since I've made it, so
I'll just make it again. The difference between אמר מר amar mar
and גופא. gufa. Both of those go back to a Tannaitic source
that we've quoted and that we're now going to look at in
greater detail. But אמר מר amar mar is when we've quoted the
entire text and now we're going to look at piece by piece.
We're going to what, unpack it, right? So that's what we did.
We quoted a nice big ברייתא braita and now we're going to
go through it line by line. That's אמר מר. amar mar. גופא
Gufa is when we had one quote from a ברייתא braita and
now we want to go back and look at the whole ברייתא.
braita. Okay? So this is when you have the whole thing, right,
you got the whole thing, okay, and you got the whole big
thing here, and now we're going to אמר מר, amar mar, now
let's unpack it and look at each piece of it. Okay, that's
אמר מר. amar mar. גופא Gufa is when you have a little
piece of it and then you say, now let's look at the
whole big thing, and you quote the whole ברייתא braita and then
you... All right, אמר מר. Amar Mar. So now let's unpack this
ברייתא Braisa that we just quoted.
יכול אפילו חילול שבת, Yakhol afilu chillul Shabbos, maybe even if she
desecrated שבת, Shabbos, maybe if this, right, כי תחל Ki teichel and
את אביה היא מחללת. Es aviha hi mechaleles. So let's just bracket
the word לזנות, Liznos, obviously rejected because of the word לזנות. Liznos.
But maybe this applies even to somebody who violated שבת. Shabbos. So
the גמרא Gemara says, חילול שבת בסקילה היא. Chillul Shabbos biskilah hi.
How could I think that חילול שבת Chillul Shabbos gets שריפה, Sreifah,
besides the word לזנות? Liznos? חילול שבת Chillul Shabbos we know is
סקילה, Skilah, that's one of the classic things, the guy who was
מקושש עצים Mekoshesh etzim and they go and they stone him. So
אמר רבא המני רבי שמעון היא דאמר שריפה
חמורה. Amar Rava hamani Rabbi Shimon hi de'amar sreifah chamurah. First of
all, this ברייתא Braisa is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that assumes that
שריפה Sreifah is worse. You sort of know that because the ברייתא
Braisa also assumed that the בת איש כהן Bas ish kohen assumed
that she gets שריפה Sreifah whether she's a נשואה Nesuah or an
ארוסה. Arusah. So that's going to work with that assumption that שריפה
Sreifah is always worse. So we do have, it's true שבת Shabbos
gets סקילה, Skilah, but there's a possibility within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that in a worse violation you get שריפה. Sreifah. שריפה Sreifah is
a worse punishment.
רבי שמעון היא דאמר שריפה חמורה. Rabbi Shimon hi de'amar sreifah chamurah.
וסלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל ואחמרה בה רחמנא בכהני, Vesalka daitach amina ho'il
ve'achmrah bah Rachmana bekhahanei, since the תורה Torah is often very strict
with כהנים, Kohanim, דרבי בהו מצות יתירות, Derabi behu mitzvos yeseros, they
have all these extra מצות, Mitzvos, all these extra obligations and all
these extra prohibitions. So תידון בשריפה. Tidon besreifah. Maybe if a כהן
Kohen is מחלל שבת, Mechalel Shabbos, maybe because they represent the, they're
supposed to be the embodiment of God's תורה Torah and so on
and the religious leaders, and they have all these extra מצות, Mitzvos,
maybe their punishment will be more severe, maybe they should get שריפה
Sreifah assuming like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that שריפה Sreifah is worse.
So that was the הוה אמינא Hava amina that for חילול שבת
Chillul Shabbos this בת איש כהן Bas ish kohen would get שריפה.
Sreifah. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, so קא משמע לן
Ka mashma lan that she doesn't, that we're not talking about שבת.
Shabbos. גמרא Gemara says, one minute, מאי שנא מיניה דידיה? Mai shna
minei didei?
Why would I have thought that specifically in this case you get
שריפה? Sreifah? If כהנים Kohanim were supposed to get שריפה Sreifah because
they're supposed to be at a higher level and they get a
bigger punishment, why would דוקא Davka
this daughter of a כהן Kohen get שריפה Sreifah and not the
כהנים Kohanim themselves, not the male כהן? Kohen? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
daitach amina, I would have thought, איהו דאשתרי ליה שבת לגבי עבודה,
Ihu de'ishtarei lei Shabbos legabi avodah,
a male כהן Kohen for whom they're allowed to violate שבת Shabbos
or they're obligated to violate שבת Shabbos to do the עבודה, Avodah,
the work up in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the slaughtering of
the animals etc., the bringing of the קרבנות. Korbanos. So
therefore the תורה Torah is not, there's already allowances for שבת, Shabbos,
the תורה Torah is not going to give this weighty punishment. But
היא, Hi, but for a כהן Kohen daughter, כיון דלא אשתרי שבת
לגבה, Keivan delo ishtarei Shabbos legabah, on the one hand she's from
a כהן Kohen family so the responsibility is weightier, on the other
hand she never has an allowance for שבת, Shabbos, so I might
have thought אימא תידון בשריפה, Eima tidon besreifah, I might have thought
give her שריפה, Sreifah, give her a heavier punishment. קא משמע לן
Ka mashma lan that you don't. So that was a crazy הוה
אמינא Hava amina but it's so classic even if it's a crazy
הוה אמינא Hava amina that's immediately going to be dismissed because it
says the word לזנות. Liznos. We want to at least understand what
was the הוה אמינא, Hava amina, what could I have been thinking?
And maybe I would have thought if שריפה Sreifah is a worse
punishment, maybe a female כהן, Kohen, a daughter of a כהן Kohen
gets שריפה Sreifah for חילול שבת Chillul Shabbos because she's from this
family and she has a higher standard to uphold. But then we
say that's not what we're talking about, says כי
תחל לזנות. Ki teichel liznos. We're talking about an act of forbidden
sex. So the
גמרא Gemara says יכול אפילו פנויה, Yakhol afilu pnuyah, if it says
לזנות, Liznos, maybe we're talking even if she's not married, she's just,
maybe that's a reasonable read of the פסוק. Pasuk. You have to
preserve the status of the כהן Kohen house, so maybe even if
she's just sleeping around, maybe that's this punishment, maybe it has nothing
to do with adultery. And the גמרא Gemara learns out it's not
because it says אביה Aviha here and it says אביה Aviha by
נערה מאורסה, Naarah meorasah, so you know that she's married. But that
was the הוה אמינא, Hava amina, יכול אפילו פנויה. Yakhol afilu pnuyah.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, לזנות כתיב, Liznos kesiv, but
it says לזנות, Liznos, doesn't לזנות Liznos mean adultery? Now that's funny
because when we hear the word of זנות, Znus, we don't think
of adultery, we think of just normal type of promiscuous sex. The
fact that a woman in a פשט Peshat in the תורה Torah
is called a זונה Zonah is not about the fact that she
is committing the act of adultery, it's about the fact that she's
just having sex with whatever man pays her price. I do have
to by the way share this great פשט Peshat by Robert Alter,
a brilliant read of because there's two words in the תורה Torah
for a prostitute, one is a זונה Zonah and the other is
a
קדשה. Kedeishah. And so the classic explanation, I mean why קדשה, Kedeishah,
קדוש Kadosh etc., the classic explanation is that לרש"י ואחרים Le-Rashi ve-acherim
is that means קדשה Kedeishah means like designated, she's designated for this
role
of sex and so on
of hiring herself for sex. But Robert Alter says and he reads
this in the whole story by יהודה Yehudah and תמר. Tamar. that
no, there's a difference. זונה zonah is about זנות, znus, is just
your standard prostitute, right? Whereas a קדשה, k'desha, from the word קדוש,
kadosh, is a cult prostitute, somebody who does it in the context
of some type of a religious temple act. So he says if
you look at the story of יהודה Yehuda and תמר, Tamar, right?
When יהודה Yehuda sees תמר, Tamar, it says that he saw ויחשבה
לזונה vayachsheveha le'zonah כי כסתה פניה. ki chisseta paneha. He thought that
she was a זונה. zonah. Okay,
so he hired her, right? And then when he goes back to
look for her to get back his staff and his ring or
whatever, he sends his friend and his friend says איה הקדשה ayeh
hakedesha היא בעינים על הדרך. hi va'einayim al haderech. So he says
you didn't want to go around announcing the fact that you had
hired the services of a normal prostitute. Oh, if you were with
a cult prostitute, that's already more כשר, kosher, that's okay. So he
was trying to sort of hide it, so he was asking around
for a קדשה. k'desha. So they said לא היתה בזה קדשה. lo
hayta vazeh kedesha. Cult prostitutes we don't have. Like זונות zonas we
have plenty of, but קדשות kdeshas we don't have any קדשות. kdeshas.
That's why he couldn't find her. So anyway, but it's very interesting.
Anyway, the word זנות, znus, if I don't know, I haven't looked
at what like the biblical scholars say or whatever, but I would
think it just generally means sort of promiscuous or
non-regulated sexuality. But the גמרא Gemara here assumes that the word זנות
znus specifically means some form of a violation, some form of an
act of like adultery or a forbidden an act of forbidden sexual
act that's forbidden, not just because it's not in the context of
marriage. So it says, how could I have thought that the word
לזנות בית אביה, liznos beis aviha. כי תחל לזנות ki techal liznos
means just an unmarried woman? לזנות liznos has to mean some more
forbidden act of sex. Okay, if you look, so the גמרא's Gemara
answer is, no, maybe it does mean a broader sense of sexual
activity. כתיב ktiv סיפא seifa כרבי אליעזר. ki'Rabbi Eliezer. No, we were
thinking like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דאמר de'amar רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says that the word זונה zonah and זנות znus does mean more
a broader sense of sex outside of marriage. פנוי הבא על פנויה,
panui haba al pnuyah, even a single man with a single woman,
nobody is married, no violation, certainly not on the woman's part, even
for a man it really isn't seen הלכתית halachicly as the same
because it's not monogamy from the man's perspective. But even if everybody
is single and there's no marriage here, nevertheless if they שלא לשם
אישות, she'lo l'shem ishus, if they have an act of intercourse without
the context of marriage, it's just casual sex, in that case, עשאה
זונה. asa'ah zonah. That is the זונה zonah in the תורה Torah
when it says that a כהן kohen cannot marry a זונה, zonah,
אשה זונה וחללה לא יקחו. ishah zonah vechalalah lo yikachu. So what
is the זונה? zonah? So normally, the normal הלכה halacha is that
a זונה zonah is a woman who has engaged in an act
of forbidden sex with a man for whom it is forbidden for
her to marry, like the רמב״ם Rambam says for example, that it's
not every act of forbidden sex. If a woman let's say is
a נדה niddah and has sex as a נדה, niddah, then she
is not a זונה zonah because the sex was not with a
man that she's forbidden to marry. But any act of sex with
a man she's forbidden to marry makes her into a זונה. zonah.
Okay, so that's זונה, zonah, the word זנות znus specifically like the
גמרא Gemara initially assumed, that it's in the context
of a forbidden act of sex. But here you have the position
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that the word זנות znus and זונה
zonah means any sex outside of marriage. Okay, so that's what we
initially thought. We initially thought that therefore we could be talking even
about a single woman and the word לזנות liznos means any sex
outside of marriage. So עשאה זונה. asa'ah zonah. אינו
אומר eino omer אביה aviha אלא ela
okay fine. So then it says קמשמע לן ka mashma lan the
link of בית אביה beis aviha, and בית אביה beis aviha tells
us that she is married. Okay? So you got it? So we're
going through the פסוק, pasuk, so we have
כי תחל לזנות. ki techal liznos. So תחל techal we saw maybe
it means חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, right? That was the first thing
we say, no it can't be חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, it says
לזנות. liznos Okay, we thought לזנות liznos. means maybe even פנויה pnuyah
because maybe there's an idea that זנות znus is talking about פנויה
pnuyah and we say no it doesn't mean that. בית אביה beis
aviha based on the idea of בית אביה, beis aviha לזנות liznos
means זיקת הבעל. zikat habaal. Okay,
זיקת הבעל. zikat habaal. So that's where we're up to. Okay, we're
talking about forbidden sex with being married. Okay, now we continue.
One point is that זנות znus doesn't necessarily point to בית אביה
beis aviha, when the thing says,
oh
no, the word בית אביה beis aviha doesn't mean marriage. It's because
by it says by the נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah, it says by
the woman who is the betrothed maiden, that when she sins it
speaks about that she is like לזנות liznos בית אביה. beis aviha
So okay, so it's since in another place in the תורה Torah
it speaks about a woman in her father's home doing an act
of זנות znus and being The מאורסה, me'urasa, it says by the
woman who is the betrothed maiden that when she sins it speaks
about that she is like בית אביה. Beit Aviha. Since in another
place in the תורה Torah it speaks about a woman in her
father's
home doing an act of זנות zenut and being liable the death
penalty and there it's explicit that she's מאורסה, me'urasa, we borrow that
we make the parallel here. But there's nothing implicit in the words
בית אביה Beit Aviha that means that she's married. It's by a
link to a parallel case. Okay, yes? And/or unless by saying בית
אביה Beit Aviha we imply that there's another בית, bayit, like otherwise
you don't have, you don't need it.
She could be the בית אביה Beit Aviha suggests that there's another
house in the offing there. That could be. Right. Okay, that could
be. But specifically it's also the link to נערה מאורסה. Na'ara Me'urasa.
Anyway, so that's that. That we say like
this. Now, או אינו אומר אלא אומר אביה להוציא את כל האדם
אלא O eno omar ela omar aviha lehotzi et kol ha-adam ela
so then the ברייתא Braita continues: Maybe בית אביה Beit Aviha doesn't
just mean she's married, maybe בית אביה Beit Aviha means by the
link to נערה מאורסה Na'ara Me'urasa maybe בית אביה Beit Aviha means
that the act that she's done is slept with her father and
it excludes sleeping with another man? So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
and what's the הוה אמינא hava amina there? The גמרא Gemara says
אלא מאי אלא מאי נו שזינתה מאביה? ella mai ella mai nu
shezinta me'aviha? What, the הוה אמינא hava amina now that she slept
with her father? So מאי איריא בת כהן? mai irya Bat Kohen?
If we're talking about the sin of sleeping with a father and
a daughter and that gets שריפה sreifa elsewhere in the תורה, Torah,
why do we specifically talking in the בת כהן Bat Kohen context?
אפילו בת ישראל נמי, afillu Bat Yisrael nami, even in any, you
know, Jewish woman. דאמר רבא אמר לי רב יצחק בר אבדימי אתיא
הנה הנה אתיא זמה זמה. de-amar Rava amar li Rav Itzchak bar
Avdimi atya hena hena atya zima zima. So it says by a
man who sleeps with his granddaughter, that's actually interesting, the תורה Torah
never explicitly talks about a man who sleeps with his daughter, it
says a man who sleeps with his granddaughter, רש"י Rashi quotes the
פסוק pasuk ערוות בת בנו בת בתו ערוות בת בנך או בת
בתך כי ערוותך הנה. ervat bat bino bat bito ervat bat binkha
o bat bitkha ki ervatkha hena. Okay, so it says
by
granddaughter כי ערוותך הנה. ki ervatkha hena. And it says
stepdaughter ערוות אישה ובתה לא תגלה את בת בנה ואת
בת בתה לא תקח לגלות ערוותה שארה הנה זמה היא.
ervat isha u-vitah
lo tegaleh et bat benah ve-et bat bitah lo tikach legalot ervatah
she'era hena zima hi. Okay, so we have
by right, by by granddaughter it says ערוותך
הנה,
ervatkha
hena, and by stepdaughter,
wife's daughter or step granddaughter,
granddaughter, sorry my writing here, it says the end of the פסוק
pasuk is what's
the פסוק? pasuk? לא תקח שארה הנה זמה היא.
lo tikach she'era hena
zima hi. Okay, so first of all, the first thing we do
is we link the הנהs hena and we say because this is
only talks about granddaughter, the question is how do you know that
daughter is forbidden? Maybe only granddaughter is forbidden. I mean we have
granddaughter, we have stepdaughter, we have step granddaughter, okay, but we don't
have daughter. So the הנה hena links and since here granddaughter is
also includes daughter, this also includes daughter. So that's one thing you
get from the link is the הנה. hena. But now how do
you know about the punishment? So in ויקרא כ Vayikra Chaf it
says it says it says אישה ובתה לא תקח isha u-vitah lo
tikach what's the פסוק? pasuk? In
ויקרא כ Vayikra Chaf it says
ואיש אשר יקח את אישה ואת אמה זמה היא באש ישרפו אותו
ואתהן. ve-ish asher yikach et isha ve-et imah zima hi ba-esh yisrefu
oto ve-et-hen. Okay, so it says אישה ואמה isha ve-imah which is
the same as a woman and her daughter is a woman and
her mother, it says באש ישרפו ba-esh yisrefu what does it say?
ואיש אשר ישכב את אישה
ואת אמה זמה
היא באש ישרפו.
ve-ish asher yishkav et isha ve-et imah zima
hi ba-esh yisrefu. Okay, so this זמה zima and this זמה zima
is actually the same thing tells you that the case of the
stepdaughter gets שריפה. sreifa. Okay? You see that this is actually the
same thing. This is ויקרא י"ח Vayikra Yud Chet where it says
don't do it, and this ויקרא כ Vayikra Chaf where it says
the punishment. Here it phrases it as a woman and her daughter,
here it phrases it as a woman and her mother. You can
figure out that that's the same thing. Okay? So it's the same
word זמה, zima, it's the same thing, it tells you it gets
שריפה. sreifa. The word היא הנה hi hena lets you link the
story of stepdaughter to the case of granddaughter and tells you that
granddaughter is. It also applies to daughter and it also gets the
punishment of שריפה. sreifa. Tal, you had a question?
So it says באש ישרפו
אותו?
ba'esh
yisrefu oto? אותו ואתהן, oto ve'ethen, right. But she...
he also. This takes, it's only the בת כהן. bat kohen. Okay?
So this is telling you that it includes daughter, it's not just
granddaughter because the case of the step includes daughter, and it's telling
you that it gets שריפה. sreifa. Okay? That's the case of the
of the woman and her daughter, but not the man's own daughter.
And the הנה hena links it back to the man's own. So
granddaughter would include daughter and would get שריפה.
sreifa. What does he get?
He gets the same. It's only by the בת כהן bat kohen
that she gets a separate punishment. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says,
so דאמר רבא אמר לי רב יוסף בר אבדימי אתיא הנה הנה
אתיא זימה זימה. d'amar Rava amar li Rav Yosef bar Abdimi atya
hena hena atya zima zima.
So we know that a woman with her father gets שריפה. sreifa.
So how could the בת איש כהן bat ish kohen be talking
about her father, then it wouldn't be unique to being a בת
איש כהן? bat ish kohen? Every woman, that would be true. איצטריך,
itztrich, I need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא קרא לאפוקי מדרבא. salka datach
amina kra l'apokei mid'Rava. No, I would have actually thought that the
פסוק pasuk by the בת כהן bat kohen is telling you to
reject this דרשה, drasha, to say that only a בת כהן bat
kohen with her father gets שריפה. sreifa. A normal daughter with her
father does not get שריפה. sreifa. מדי גלי רחמנא בבת כהן ולא
בבת ישראל. midei gali Rachmana b'vat kohen v'lo b'vat Yisrael.
I would have said not to say against what we know the
הלכה halacha to be, that a בת כהן bat kohen with her
father gets שריפה, sreifa, but a normal daughter with her father does
not.
קמ"ל ka mashma lan that every daughter with her father it would
be the punishment of שריפה. sreifa. Okay? So that's to remove the
possibility that the פסוק pasuk is just talking about her and her
father. בת כהן. bat kohen. אין לי אלא. ein li ela. Now
okay, so that's where we... so the בת כהן bat kohen tells
me that it is with any man and not just with her
father. Okay, I forgot how we got that from the word בת
כהן, bat kohen, oh no, היא מחללת. hi mechalelet. We learned it
from the word היא מחללת. hi mechalelet. That את אביה היא מחללת,
et aviha hi mechalelet, she is desecrating her father, her father isn't
violating and desecrating her. Okay? So we learn from back to here,
so כי תחל לזנות. ki techal liznot.
Okay? So now, את אביה היא מחללת. et aviha hi mechalelet. So
we would have said maybe אביה aviha means, maybe it means that
she was מזנה עם אביה, mezana im aviha, maybe she actually had
sex with her father and only that woman would get שריפה, sreifa,
other women who had sex with her father would not. So it
says no. היא מחללת hi mechalelet tells you that she is the
one who is doing the sin, not him. Okay? So therefore we
know that she slept with another man. Okay? So she did a
forbidden act of sex, she's married to another man, and she slept
with somebody not her father. Okay? And now we continue. Okay?
So,
יא אין לי אלא בת כהן אין לי אלא שניסת לכהן. ya
ein li ela bat kohen ein li ela sheniset l'kohen. Maybe only
if she's married to a כהן. kohen. ניסת ללוי לישראל ולעובד כוכבים
ומזלות ולחלל ולנתין ולממזר מניין? niset l'Levi l'Yisrael u'l'Oved Kochavim u'mazalot u'l'chalal
u'l'natin u'l'mamzer minayin? How do I know if she's married to some
other type of a man that that would still be a violation
of her כהונה kehuna status, you know, and it would still get
the same punishment? תלמוד לומר בת איש כהן, talmud lomar bat ish
kohen, the daughter of a כהן, kohen, אף על פי שאינה כהנת,
af al pi she'eina kohenet, even though her own כהונה kehuna status
has already been somewhat compromised. So the גמרא Gemara says, what's the
הוה אמינא hava amina here? משום דאינסבה להו להני לאו בת כוהני?
mishum d'inseiva lehu l'hanei lav bat kohani? So I don't understand, because
she's married to like a ישראל Yisrael or לוי, Levi, she stops
being a בת כהן? bat kohen? Why would I have thought that
who she's married to would have mattered? So the גמרא Gemara says,
וכי מדי כוהנת לכהן כתיב? v'chi midei kohenet l'kohen ktiv? I don't
understand. Since when does it say that a daughter of a כהן
kohen has to marry a כהן? kohen? Like why would I have
thought that married to some other man would be different? A daughter
of a כהן kohen is free to marry whomever she wants. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no.
סלקא דעתך אמינא כי תחל לזנות אמר רחמנא. salka datach amina ki
techal liznot amar Rachmana. When she begins to be, you know, to
commit an act of adultery and when this act of sex brings
some type of a חילול, chilul, some type of a desecration to
her קדושה kedusha status. So הני מילי hanei milei maybe this punishment
is היכא דקמיתחלא השתא heicha d'kamitchala hashta when... so I think the
word תחל techal is like a double meaning, להתחיל lehatchil and לחלל.
lechalel. This is the first act of violating her כהונה kehuna status.
אבל הא, aval ha, a woman who married somebody who isn't a
כהן, kohen, כיון דקמיתחלא וקיימא, keivan d'kamitchala v'kayma, that's already to some
degree compromised her כהונה kehuna status. How has that been? מעיקרא. mei'ikara.
Now how do I know that marrying a non-כהן kohen would have
compromised her כהונה kehuna status? דאמר מר, d'amar mar, because we've taught,
ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר היא בתרומת הקדשים לא תאכל. v'vat
kohen ki tihye l'ish zar hi bi'trumat ha'kodashim lo tochel.
If a daughter of a כהן kohen marries some other man then
she cannot eat תרומה. truma. She can only eat תרומה truma if
she's married to a כהן kohen or if she is in her
father's house, her father's a כהן kohen and she's not married to
another man. But if she's married to a man who's not a
כהן, kohen, the house she's connected house she was no longer a
כהונה Kehunah house. Because she's married, she's not connected to her father's
house, and because her husband isn't a כהן, Kohen, she's not connected
to a כהונה Kehunah house. Everybody get that? So when she's married
to a non-כהן, Kohen, she can't eat תרומה. Trumah. So כיוון, keivan,
now the הלכה Halacha is the following: not only can she, now
if she's just married to ישראל Yisrael and a לוי Levi and
it's a kosher marriage, then if she gets divorced or the husband
dies and there's no child, then she goes back to her father's
house and she once again is reabsorbed into the father's כהן Kohen
house and she continues to eat תרומה. Trumah. Okay, so being married
to a כהן Kohen or a לוי Levi only temporarily puts her
outside of the כהונה Kehunah household. But if the man she was
married to is somebody she's forbidden to be married to, like the
people we were talking about, like a ממזר, Mamzer, a non-Jew, something
of that, that doesn't just temporarily remove her from her כהונה Kehunah
status, that changes her status altogether. She can never return to her
father's house to eat תרומה. Trumah. Her כהונה Kehunah status has been
violated, okay? So this is a way in which, what does it
mean for a כהונה Kehunah status to be violated by a woman?
It would mean that if she's a daughter of a כהן, Kohen,
even if she's no longer married to a man, she cannot go
back to her father's, I mean she can always go back to
the physical house, but she cannot go back to the conceptual house
to continue to eat תרומה. Trumah. Okay, and when would that be?
If she was married to a man that is forbidden to her.
Okay, so we say,
כיון שנבעלה לפסולה, keivan sheniv'ala le-psula, once she had sex with a
man that is forbidden to her, פסלה, pasla, that invalidates her. So
if she's married to a ממזר Mamzer or a נתין Netin or
a non-Jew, now a חלל, Chalal, interesting, a חלל, Chalal, like a
כהן Kohen is let's say born of a גרושה Gerusha and a
כהן. Kohen. It's permissible for a בת כהן Bas Kohen to marry
a חלל. Chalal. There's no איסור issur involved. But nevertheless, חלל Chalal
is like contagious. Okay, the irony is that a כהן Kohen who
does a sin, his status never changes. A כהן Kohen marries a
גרושה, Gerusha, he's still, I mean we don't let him דוכנ'ן duchen
until he divorces the woman, but that's more of a קנס, knas,
Halachically his status has not changed. But his child is a חלל.
Chalal. And his son who's a חלל Chalal who's born of that
union, if he has sex with a woman, even a woman he's
married to, even though it's completely Halachically permissible, that status transfers to
the woman and she becomes a חללה. Chalalla. Okay, so this daughter
of a כהן Kohen that is married either to a נתין, Netin,
a ממזר, Mamzer, a non-Jew, who it's forbidden for her to marry
and that violates her status, or a חלל, Chalal, it's permissible to
her status, but then she becomes a חללה, Chalalla, any of those
cases,
that has changed her status. And now she cannot, a, marry a
כהן, Kohen, that's one way to prove it's changed her status. She's
now herself a חללה Chalalla or זונה Zonah or whatever, she can't
marry a כהן. Kohen. And number two, she can't eat תרומה. Trumah.
So that would be a case where her כהונה Kehunah status has
already been violated. So maybe if after that she went ahead and
committed adultery with somebody else, it's a terrible sin, but it's not
ואת אביה היא מחללת. et aviha hi mechaleles. She's already compromised her
כהונה Kehunah status. That's not a bad הוה אמינא. hava amina. Okay,
not only that, maybe even if she's just married to a לוי
Levi and a
ישראל. Yisrael. Okay, דאמר רב ששת, d'amar Rav Sheshet, לוי וישראל נמי,
Levi ve-Yisrael nami, and in לוי Levi and ישראל, Yisrael, even though
right now her status hasn't been compromised in any permanent way, but
והשבה אל בית אביה כנעוריה, v'hashava el beis aviha k'neuraiha, only after
her husband לוי Levi ישראל Yisrael died would she be able to
return to her father's house. Right now she can't eat תרומה. Trumah.
So right now being married to a לוי Levi ישראל Yisrael takes
her out of her כהונה Kehunah status. מכלל דכי איתא גבי, mikhlal
d'ki isa gabei, when she's still with him, לא אכלה, lo akhla,
she doesn't eat תרומה. Trumah. So this בת כהן Bas Kohen that's
married to a לוי Levi ישראל, Yisrael, certainly a נתין, Netin, ממזר,
Mamzer, whatever, her כהונה Kehunah status has either temporarily or permanently been
compromised. And therefore maybe it wouldn't be the same sin if she
committed adultery and maybe she wouldn't get punished by שריפה. sreifa. So
אימא לא תידון בשריפה, eima lo tidon be-sreifa, she'd still be committing
adultery, she'd still get executed, but maybe not שריפה. sreifa. קא משמע
לן kama mashma lan that she does. Okay, so now the הוה
אמינא hava amina is not so bad, especially the case of the
נתין Netin and the ממזר Mamzer whatever, right, if having slept with
them she's now forbidden to a כהן, Kohen, she can't eat תרומה,
Trumah, all those things, maybe
it, excuse me, no, as long as she's a בת כהן, Bas
Kohen, this punishment always applies. ודלא כרבי מאיר, u-dlo k'Rabbi Meir, not
like Rabbi Meir,
דתניא, d'tanya, בת כהן שנישאת לישראל ואכלה תרומה משלמת את הקרן ואינה
משלמת את החומש. Bas Kohen shenis'sa le-Yisrael v'akhla trumah m'shalemes es hakeren
v'eina m'shalemes es hachomesh. So a בת כהן Bas Kohen who's married
to ישראל Yisrael and she eats תרומה, Trumah, okay, so she's not
entitled to תרומה Trumah because she's married to ישראל. Yisrael. So she
pays the principal, but she doesn't add the fifth, because the fifth
is only for a זר, zar, a foreigner like a non-כהן Kohen
who eats the תרומה. Trumah. So this בת כהן Bas Kohen who's
married to ישראל, Yisrael, even though now she's forbidden to eat תרומה,
Trumah, since she came from a household that she could eat תרומה,
Trumah, and were her husband to die without a child she would
go back to eating תרומה, Trumah, she's not considered to be a
complete זר zar vis-a-vis תרומה. Trumah. So she doesn't pay the special
fine that the זר zar pays when he eats תרומה. Trumah. Okay,
that's the בת כהן bat Kohen, *Bat Kohen*. ומיתתה בשריפה *umissasa b'shreifa*.
Now she will, if she commits adultery, she's going to get שריפה
sereifah *shreifa*, that's our פרשה *parsha*. נישאת לאחר *nisas l'acher*, לאחד מן
הפסולים *l'achad min hapsulim*, however, let's say she's married to a man
who invalidates her, like this ממזר *mamzer* or something like that. In
that case, she'll never go back to eating תרומה *Truma*. Her status
has been compromised. משלמת קרן וחומש *mishalemes keren v'chomesh*, you will pay
the fifth, she is now a זרה *zara*, her status has become
completely compromised. ומיתתה בחנק *umisasa b'chenek*, דברי רבי מאיר *divrei Rabbi Meir*.
Rabbi Meir says she'll no longer get שריפה sereifah, *shreifa* if she
commits adultery. She's not in that כהונה *kehuna* status. Yes, so our
ברייתא Baraita *Braisa* was explicitly to reject רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says maybe not married to a לוי *Levi*, ישראל
*Yisrael*, but certainly married to somebody who's פסול *pasul*, okay, who changes
her status permanently, that in that case she wouldn't get שריפה Sereifah
*shreifa* anymore. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. אומר *Rabbi Elazar Omer*, okay, so
anyway, so that is the end וחכמים אומרים *v'Chachamim omrim*, וחכמים *v'Chachamim*
say, זו וזו משלמת קרן ולא חומש *zo v'zo mishalemes keren v'lo
chomesh*, even after her status has been compromised, she still doesn't pay
a חומש *chomesh*, because she came from a status of being a
בת כהן bat Kohen *Bat Kohen*, and ומיתתה בשריפה *umisasa b'shreifa*, and
it would be a punishment of שריפה sereifah. *shreifa* even after this,
you know, this act and now she can't eat תרומה *Truma* and
now she can't marry a כהן *Kohen*, she still has she's still
connected to the כהן *Kohen* house. And because she's still connected to
the כהן *Kohen* house, she'll never pay a חומש *chomesh*, and if
she commits adultery she'll always get שריפה sereifah. *shreifa*. I guess having
that קדושה *kedusha* status has its pluses and minuses. So okay, now,
so now we've done that, it doesn't matter who she's married to.
Even married to somebody פסול *pasul*, she still is going to get
שריפה sereifah, *shreifa*, she's still violating the כהונה *kehuna* status. Now, let's
keep on going. נישאת לאחד מן הפסולים *nisas l'achad min hapsulim*, I
just did that. Okay. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Elazar Omer*,
את אביה aviha בשריפה *es aviha b'shreifa*, the last line of the
ברייתא Baraita. *Braisa*, a very curious line. את אביה aviha בשריפה ואת
חמיה Ve'et chamia, בסקילה *es aviha b'shreifa v'es chamiha b'skila*. With her
father it's שריפה sereifah *shreifa*, with her father-in-law it's סקילה skila, *skila*.
Huh? What does he mean? מאי את אביה ואת חמיה chamia *mai
es aviha v'es chamiha*? What is he talking about? אילימא את אביה
מאביה ואת חמיה chamia מחמיה *ileima es aviha me'aviha v'es chamiha mechamiha*?
If it means that she slept with her father. If this בת
איש כהן *Bat ish kohen* sleeps with her father, so a daughter
and her father get שריפה sereifah, *shreifa*, we said that. If she
sleeps with her father-in-law, then that's a normal act of adultery and
that's סקילה skila. *skila*. Okay, that's interesting, but like why do we
care? That's just has nothing to do with בת איש כהן *Bat
ish kohen*. That's just telling us the general sin
of with the father is שריפה sereifah *shreifa* and with adultery is
סקילה skila. *skila*. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. מאי
איריא בת כהן bat Kohen *mai irya Bat Kohen*? אפילו בת ישראל
bat Yisrael, נמי *afillu Bat Yisrael nami*! בתו בשריפה וכלתו בסקילה *bito
b'shreifa v'chalaso b'skila*, that's just the general rule, okay, that a daughter
is שריפה sereifah *shreifa* and a daughter-in-law is סקילה skila *skila*. It's
interesting that he's saying that, but has nothing to do with the
unique issues of בת איש כהן *Bat ish kohen*. אלא את אביה
ברשות אביה birshus aviha ואת חמיה chamia ברשות חמיה chamia. *ella es
aviha birshus aviha v'es chamiha birshus chamiha*. Okay no, so what he
means is whose house is she a part of? Okay, so here
we're going to go back to
this issue,
right, about who gets about who gets what do you call it,
who gets which punishment, right? So you remember, a בת ישראל *Bat
Yisrael* נשואה nesua *nesuah* gets חנק chenek *chenek* and ארוסה arusa *arusah*
gets סקילה skila. *skila*. By a בת כהן *Bat Kohen*, who are
we talking about? So it's שריפה sereifah. *shreifa*. So the position of
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* that says שריפה sereifah *shreifa*'s always
weightier, which has also been the position so far of this ברייתא
braisa *Braisa*, is that both of these cases,
gotta get rid of this pen, both of these cases get שריפה
sereifah *shreifa*, okay? That's been the position of him and שריפה sereifah
*shreifa* is worse than both of these. Okay. Now, here we want
to say one minute, this case of ארוסה arusa, *arusah*, ארוסה arusa
*arusah* which house is she in? She's in בית אביה *Beis Aviha*,
right? She's in her father's house. נשואה nesua *nesuah*, she's in her
husband's house. Her husband's house, assuming you move in with the husband's
family, would be according to this, בית חמיה *Beis Chamiha*, okay, or
בית בעלה *Beis Ba'alah*. Okay, so
what he's what we're trying to interpret and saying is: את אביה
*es aviha*,
if she's in her father's house, she's going to get שריפה sereifah,
*shreifa*. את חמיה *es
chamiha*, if she's married, she's going to get סקילה skila. *skila*. Now,
in theory that would be possible if you follow the position of
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* that שריפה sereifah, *shreifa* is worse
than סקילה skila. *skila*, okay, so when she's an ארוסה arusa *arusah*
it's worse, that's always assumed to be worse, שריפה sereifah. *shreifa*, and
this is not as bad as סקילה skila, *skila*. But the problem
is where do you get סקילה skila. *skila*? Meaning you could say
חנק chenek *chenek*, right? But where would you learn out that she
would get סקילה skila *skila* if she's
a נשואה *nesuah*? But this is how we're reading it. It's a
reasonable read of the position. In her father's house she gets שריפה
sereifah *shreifa*, that's what's in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. שריפה sereifah *shreifa*,
שריפה *shreifa* is worse than סקילה Skila. *skila*, okay, and if she's
not if she's in her husband's house, then it's not going to
be שריפה *shreifa*, it'll be סקילה skila *skila*. But where did that
סקילה skila *skila* come from? Okay, so let's take a look at
logically it works, but where did it come from? So let's take
a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. ואת חמיה *v'es chamiha*...
את חמיה *es chameha*. כמאן *Keman*? אי כרבנן *Ee k'rabanan*, if it's
the rabbis, הא אמי נישואה יצאה לשרפה ולא ארוסה arusa *Ha ami
nisuah yatza l'sreifah v'lo arusah*. Now the rabbis say that סקילה skila,
*skila*'s worse, so for the rabbis, right, how do they do this?
They say the שרפה sreifa. *sreifa* in the פסוק *pasuk* is up
here, right, because they have to keep since סקילה skila. *skila*'s for
ארוסה arusa *arusa* by בת ישראל *bas yisrael*, they have to keep
סקילה skila. *skila*,
סקילה skila. *skila*'s the weightier one. Okay, so remember that? The rabbis
said the נישואה *nisuah* was the שרפה sreifa. *sreifa* and the ארוסה
arusa *arusa* was the סקילה skila, *skila*. They had to put the
שרפה *sreifa*, limit it to the נישואה *nisuah* because they had to
keep this as the weightier one. So that's the exact flip of
what we just said. Okay, so that doesn't work. People remember that
from yesterday, more or less? Okay. אי כרבנן הא אמי נישואה יצאה
לשרפה ולא ארוסה *Ee k'rabanan ha ami nisuah yatza l'sreifah v'lo arusah*.
אי כרבי שמעון הא אמר אחת ארוסה ואחת נשואה בשרפה *Ee k'Rebbi
Shimon ha amar achas arusa v'achas nisuah b'sreifah*. Now רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon? *Rebbi Shimon* himself says they both get שרפה *sreifa*. So that's
not what you just said. ואי כרבי ישמעאל *V'ee k'Rebbi Yishmael*, now
רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael *Rebbi Yishmael* we're going to see in a
minute, we haven't seen it yet, הא אמר ארוסה יצאה לשרפה ולא
נשואה *ha amar arusa yatza l'sreifah v'lo nisuah*. So רבי ישמעאל Rebbi
Yishmael. *Rebbi Yishmael* is the closest. רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael *Rebbi Yishmael*
says שרפה *sreifa* is more חמור *chamur*, so yes, the ארוסה *arusa*
is going to get שרפה *sreifa*, but he's going to say, okay,
that's the more strict one, שרפה *sreifa*, so that'll be instead of
סקילה *skila* it'll be שרפה *sreifa*. What am I going to do
with the נישואה *nisuah*? Well, he'll say, okay, the נישואה *nisuah* I'll
just keep as the normal נישואה *nisuah*, I'll say חנק chenek. *chenek*.
So that's closest, right? Let's limit the שרפה *sreifa* in the פסוק
*pasuk* to the more severe sin, the ארוסה *arusa* case, and we'll
say שרפה *sreifa* is worse than סקילה *skila*. So we're going to
limit that. But you're not going to get סקילה *skila* up here,
the only thing you can put up here is what you know
from a normal בת ישראל *bas yisrael* is חנק chenek, *chenek*. That's
going to be רבי ישמעאל *Rebbi Yishmael*. So nobody says what we're
just reading this ברייתא braisa *Braisa* of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rebbi
Eliezer* just to say. Have I lost everybody or people more or
less? Somewhat lost, okay. Anyway. All right. So it
says, so why does it go one lower down because of בת
כהן *bas kohen*? So that's going to be the answer. The answer's
going to be it's going to follow a רבי ישמעאל *Rebbi Yishmael*
type of an approach. We'll pick the שרפה *sreifa* in the פסוק
*pasuk*, we'll say it's in the more severe case, in the ארוסה
*arusa*. And then we're able to do it if we think that
שרפה *sreifa* is weightier than סקילה *skila*. And then by analogy we're
going to say that the same way here by בת ישראל *bas
yisrael* you go down one level from סקילה *skila* to חנק chenek
*chenek*, assuming there's only one, here we'll go down one level from
שרפה *sreifa* to סקילה *skila*, right? That's a type of an argument
by analogy. That's what we're going to get to. But at this
stage we only know the closest we have is saying שרפה *sreifa*
and חנק chenek *chenek*, no analogy, just an application of the בת
ישראל *bas yisrael*. Okay, so let's see what the various answers are
going to be. Let's see if we can get to all these
answers. Okay, so it says like this. את חמיה חנק chenek, הוא
*Es chameha chenek hu*.
So that should have been if you're getting רבי ישמעאל *Rebbi Yishmael*.
שלח רבין משמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Shelach Ravin mishmei d'Rebbi Yose
b'Rebbi Chanina*. So רבין *Ravin* sent from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz
Yisrael* in the name of רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *Rebbi Yose bar
Chanina*, כך יצתה של משנה *kach yatzah shel mishna*. Here's the way
to lay out this משנה *mishna*, here's the way to explain this
ברייתא *Braisa*. לעולם כרבנן *L'olam k'rabanan*, it's like the רבנן Rabanan. *rabanan*
that say that they both get שרפה *sreifa*. So what does this
mean? והכי קאמר *V'hachi ka'amar*, כל שהוא למטה ממיתת אביה *kol shehu
l'mata mi'misas aviha*, ומאי ניהו *u'mai nihu* נישואה בת ישראל *nisuah bas
yisrael*, דאילו נישואה בת ישראל בחנק *d'ilu nisuah bas yisrael b'chenek*. So
if a woman sleeps with her father she gets שרפה *sreifa*, it's
a bizarre way of explaining this ברייתא *Braisa*. He says, so what
does it mean את אביה בשרפה es aviha bisreifa *es aviha b'sreifa*?
Anybody who is looking at the בת ישראל *bas yisrael*, okay, anybody
who is the punishment is worse, is not as bad as שרפה
*sreifa*, which is the נישואה *nisuah* case, okay, that's not as bad
as שרפה *sreifa*, that's חנק chenek, *chenek*, okay, in that case, נישואה
בת ישראל דאילו נישואה בת ישראל בחנק *nisuah bas yisrael d'ilu nisuah
bas yisrael b'chenek*, הכא במיתת אביה בשרפה *hacha b'misas aviha b'sreifa*. Then
here it would be בשרפה *b'sreifa*. So what do the רבנן Rabanan?
*rabanan* hold? The רבנן Rabanan *rabanan* hold, if you remember, right, the
רבנן Rabanan *rabanan* hold that this is שרפה *sreifa*
and this is סקילה *skila*. That's רבנן Rabanan *rabanan*. Okay, so they
say את אביה בשרפה es aviha bisreifa *es aviha b'sreifa* means anybody
over here whose punishment is lesser than שרפה *sreifa*, lesser than sleeping
with the father, that would get שרפה *sreifa*. את חמיה *es chameha*,
anybody whose punishment is worse than sleeping with the father, which would
be as if you slept with the father-in-law which would be סקילה
*skila*, so here it's going to remain סקילה *skila*. It's like a
very twisted way of just saying שרפה *sreifa* and סקילה *skila* and
I don't know, whatever, it's like you have to twist your head
to figure out why you would say it this way. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s going to more or less reject it. Let's take a
look. כל שהיא למטה ממיתת אביה *Kol shehu l'mata mi'misas aviha*, ומאי
ניהו *u'mai nihu* נישואה בת ישראל *nisuah bas yisrael* דאילו נישואה בת
ישראל בחנק *d'ilu nisuah bas yisrael b'chenek*, somebody who normally would get
something less than שרפה *sreifa*, הכא במיתת אביה *hacha b'misas aviha* here
בשרפה *b'sreifa*. So a נישואה *nisuah* will get שרפה *sreifa*. כל שהיא
למעלה ממיתת אביה *Kol shehu l'mala mi'misas aviha*, ומאי ניהו *u'mai nihu*
ארוסה בת ישראל *arusa bas yisrael*, anybody whose punishment would be worse
than שרפה *sreifa*, than having slept with the father, which would be
an ארוסה *arusa*, דאילו ארוסה *d'ilu arusa*... דאילו ארוסה בת ישראל בעלמא
בסקילה normally would get סקילה, הכא במיתת חמיה בסקילה. hacha bemitat chamia
biskila.
So in this type of a case, you're going to get סקילה.
Okay, basically, it's a very complicated way of saying that if you're
a נשואה you get שריפה and if you're an ארוסה you get
סקילה. What does it have to do with father and father-in-law and
whatever? That's what the גמרא Gemara. is going to reject. מתיב ליה
רב ירמיה: Mateiv lei Rav Yirmiya: מידי למעלה למטה קתני? Midi lemala
lemata katani? What? The ברייתא doesn't say if you're worse than the
father, if you're better than the father? Mean, come on, that's a
completely bizarre read of the ברייתא. אלא אמר רב ירמיה, Ela amar
Rav Yirmiya, let's try another read. לעולם כרבי ישמעאל. Le'olam kerabi Yishmael.
Okay, we're going to go like the רבי ישמעאל read, this gets
this read, that's the one that's closest. Okay, but we still have
the חנק chenek problem. Okay,
here's the רבי ישמעאל. Okay, לעולם כרבי ישמעאל והכי קאמר: Le'olam kerabi
Yishmael vehachi ka'amar: את אביה ברשות אביה בשריפה. Et avia birshut avia
besereifah.
Okay,
so that works, when she's in רשות אביה reshut avia it's שריפה,
that works, okay, right? שריפה she's an ארוסה, רשות אביה. reshut avia.
ואת חמיה, now what does חמיה mean? 'Cause he says חמיה is
חנק and here it says חמיה בסקילה. chamia biskila. מאי חמיה בסקילה?
Mai chamia biskila? Oh, but if she has sex with her father-in-law
then she gets סקילה if she wasn't a בת כהן, right? We're
sort of mixing and
matching. ברשות אביה בשריפה Birshut avia besereifah and now, but oh, in
a totally different case, if a girl has sex with her father-in-law
she's going to get
סקילה. וכל אדם בחנק, Vechol adam bachenek, but normal
people, בת כהן would be חנק. So the גמרא says, אמר רבא:
Amar Rava: מאי שנא? Mai shna? How are you splitting what the
words mean? או אידי ואידי ממש, O idi ve'idi mamash, either it
literally means sex with her father, sex with her father-in-law, או אידי
ואידי ברשות, o idi ve'idi birshut, or it means in her father-in-law's
domain or in her father's domain. You can't say it means in
her father's domain she's an ארוסה she gets שריפה. If she happens
to have sex with her father-in-law she gets סקילה. Like, why did
we switch gears?
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, לעולם כרבי שמעון. le'olam kerabi Shimon.
We're back to רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is,
which one is רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon Oh, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon,
is everybody gets שריפה. וקסבר רבי אליעזר, Vekasavar Rabi Eliezer, and now
here you go, Gloria, exactly like you said, נשואה כארוסה. nesua ke'arusa.
We're going to make an analogy. It really is a new position,
okay? It's a variation of the רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon, רבי ישמעאל
position. מה ארוסה חד דרגא מסקינן לה? Ma arusa chad darga maskinan
la? Okay, so here, right, by ארוסה we're going to start by
saying that that's שריפה, okay? Now שריפה for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon?
is one degree higher than סקילה. But for רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon
what's the order? The order is
שריפה, סקילה,
חנק, and הרג hereg or סייף. sayaf. Okay, so we are now
saying, I'm going to remove this, okay, and I'm going to say,
okay, so here's our analogy. We're going to start by putting שריפה
here like רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, okay? And שריפה is weightier than
סקילה. So here we see that we go one degree higher, right,
from בת כהן to בת ישראל, from סקילה to שריפה. Once we're
going to go one degree higher, what's one degree, I guess I
should have done it like this, חנק and הרג. hereg. So what's
one degree higher than חנק for רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon סקילה. So
we're going to go by analogy, right? Okay, so that's how we're
going to work it. Or you could do, you know, you could
do it the other way, you could sort of say סקילה and
חנק, סקילה is one degree higher than חנק, right? So this is
one degree higher than this, right? So שריפה and סקילה, this is
one degree higher than this, right? So it's by analogy it works.
Each thing, alright, so that's how we're going to argue this, that's
the best read I think. Okay,
מה ארוסה חד דרגא מסקינן לה, Ma arusa chad darga maskinan la,
the same way an ארוסה it goes up one
level, מסקילה לשריפה, miskila lesereifah, אף נשואה חד דרגא מסקינן לה מחנק
לסקילה. af nesua chad darga maskinan la michenek liskila. You go from
חנק to סקילה. So by analogy you're going to start with the
idea that שריפה is weightier, that שריפה applies to an ארוסה and
you're just going to say it's not everybody gets שריפה, the ארוסה
gets שריפה, the נשואה gets סקילה.
Okay, so, מתיב לה, mateiv la, that's such a good answer, but
the גמרא isn't satisfied. מתיב לה רבי חנינא: Mateiv la Rabi Chanina:
רבי חנינא Rabi Chanina asked, האי אידי ואידי רבי שמעון בשריפה קאמר.
hai idi ve'idi Rabi Shimon besereifah ka'amar. But רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
himself says they both say שריפה. Fine, so it's not רבי שמעון,
Rebbi Shimon's it's similar to רבי שמעון but somehow that bothers him.
רבי שמעון himself said they both get שריפה so it's not רבי
שמעון's position.
אלא אמר רבינא לעולם כרבנן, Ela amar Ravina le'olam kerabanan, it's the
רבנן. Rabanan So how could it be the רבנן? Rabanan The רבנן
Rabanan say, what do the רבנן Rabbanan, say? The רבנן say, what
do the רבנן say? The רבנן say it's the flip of this,
right? The רבנן say that this is שריפה because that's not as
bad and this is סקילה. Okay, okay, so now the problem is
that that's the exact inverse of that. So how can you say
it's the
rabbis? ואיפכא! Ve'eippuch! You know what? The words got mixed up. It
should have, it should have said את אביה בסקילה es aviha biskila
when she's ברשות אביה it's סקילה, ואת חמיה בשרפה ve'es chamia bisreifa
when she's in her father-in-law's domain it's שרפה. So how did it
get slipped? I mean that's very nice, but you flipped it. So
it says דהאי דקאמר סביא סריכה באלמנה קאמר. dehai deka'amar savia serikha
be'almana ka'amar. But it got flipped, it was accidental that it reversed
it. Why did it say את אביה בשרפה es aviha bisreifa. as
if it says את אביה בסקילה? es aviha biskila? Because the פסוק
says את אביה היא מחללת באש תשרף. es aviha hi mechaleles ba'esh
tisaref. So it was natural to say את אביה בשרפה or the
other way because it also says sleeping with your father is שרפה.
So it was natural, accidental, but it was a natural slip to
say את אביה בשרפה. But what it was really saying was את
אביה בסקילה, es aviha biskila, רשות אביה בסקילה reshus aviha biskila and
רשות חמיה בשרפה. reshus chamia bisreifa. So it's the רבנן, it's just
the reverse. Okay, let's just read, so we got through all the
reads. I just want to read one other sentence because it'll go
very quick. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב הלכה
כשלח רבין משמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha amar Rav halacha keshalach Ravin mishmeih deRabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina.
The way to read this ברייתא of אביה and חמיה is the
way we פסקן pasken the way it was sent there from ארץ
ישראל. I won't even remind you about what that read was, but
it was the first read. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, Rav
Yosef said, הלכתא למשיחא? hilchasa limshicha? What are you telling me this
הלכה halacha for the time of משיח? Moshiach? You know, I mean,
whatever, we're not executing nowadays, so why do I have to know
this? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, what
you think we can't talk about הלכה halacha by things that don't
apply nowadays? שחיטת קדשים לא נתני? Shechitas kodashim lo nisni? Should we
not learn all of קדשים? kodashim? Like זבחים, zvachim, מנחות, menachos, whatever,
none of that applies nowadays, even if it's הלכתא למשיחא? hilchasa limshicha?
Should we say, oh that's just for the time of משיח? Moshiach?
No! אלא דרוש וקבל שכר. Ela derush vekabel sachar. We learn it
and we explore it and we understand what the הלכה halacha will
be when it's the time of משיח. Moshiach. הכא נמי דרוש וקבל
שכר. Hacha nami derush vekabel sachar. So what bothers you that we're
פסקנינג paskening about a case about the מיתות בית דין? misos beis
din? No, הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what was bothering him.
הלכתא למה לי? Hilchasa lama li? This whole discussion was how to
read this bizarre phrase of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer There was no
הלכה halachic relevance. They were just different interpretations of the phrase. It
wasn't a הלכה halachic debate. It was just פשט pshat of what
רבי אליעזר was saying. סוגיא דשמעתא הלכתא קאמר? Sugya dishma'ta halchasa ka'amar?
It's just a discussion of what, you know, of the issue. So
what are you פסקנינג paskening a הלכה? halacha? It wasn't a הלכה
halachic issue, it was just unpacking what those words meant. So רש"י
Rashi said, you know, and the way רש"י Rashi says it, that's
what הלכתא למשיחא hilchasa limshicha means. If all you want to know
is what did רבי אליעזר mean, when משיח Moshiach comes and he
does תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim we can ask רבי אליעזר what he
meant. Okay, but it's not a הלכה halachic debate, we're just trying
to parse the words without any הלכה halachic relevance. Either way you
read the words, it's coming down to the same thing. Okay, so
that's where we ended this very bizarre last phrase of אביה and
חמיה. We finished unpacking the ברייתא and we'll continue with more of
this גמרא.